## **Daniel Bennett**

### Curriculum Vitae

School of Psychological Sciences, Monash University, Australia

phone: +61 3 9905 3598 e-mail: daniel.bennett@monash.edu website: https://bennett-daniel.github.io

# Research interests

In my research, I use the methods of computational cognitive science to understand the complex interactions between affect/emotion and cognition. I am also interested in applications of these questions to: (i) interactions between emotion, learning, and decision making in mood disorders like major depression and bipolar disorder, and (ii) the cognitive and affective processes that underlie gambling-related harm in interactive betting.

## **Employment**

Lecturer

2022-present

School of Psychological Sciences, Monash University

Research Fellow

Department of Psychiatry, Monash University

Postdoctoral Research Fellow

2017-2020

2021-2022

Princeton Neuroscience Institute, Princeton University

Advisor: Yael Niv

## Education

Doctor of Philosophy (PhD) in Psychology

2013-2017

The University of Melbourne

Thesis: Belief updating and information seeking in decision making under uncertainty Supervisors: Stefan Bode, Carsten Murawski, Rob Hester

Bachelor of Science (Honours) in Psychology

2011

The University of Melbourne

Bachelor of Science and Bachelor of Arts

2007-2010

The University of Western Australia

### **Publications**

Preprints and under review

- 1. Forbes, L. & **Bennett**, **D.** (under review). The effect of reward prediction errors on subjective affect depends on outcome valence and decision context. Preprint hosted at *PsyArXiv*: https://psyarxiv.com/v86bx
- 2. **Bennett**, **D.\***, Radulescu, A.\*, Zorowitz, S., Felso, V., & Niv, Y. (under review). Affect-congruent attention drives changes in reward expectations. Preprint hosted at *PsyArXiv*: https://psyarxiv.com/vu2cw
- 3. Lim, J. Y. L., Boardman, J. M., Anderson, C., Dickinson, D. L., **Bennett, D.**, & Drummond, S. P. A. (under review). Sleep restriction impairs the ability to

integrate multiple information sources in probabilistic decision-making. Manuscript under review.

Peer-reviewed journal articles and book chapters

- 4. Zorowitz, S., Niv, Y., Solis, J., & **Bennett, D.** (in press). Inattentive responding can induce spurious associations between task behavior and symptom measures. Manuscript accepted for publication in *Nature Human Behaviour*.
- 5. **Bennett, D.**, Nakamura, J., Vinnakota, C., Sokolenko, E., Nithianantharajah, J., van den Buuse, M., Jones, N. C., Sundram, S., & Hill, R. (in press). Mouse behaviour on the trial-unique non-matching-to-location (TUNL) touchscreen task reflects a mixture of distinct working memory codes and response biases. Manuscript accepted for publication in the *Journal of Neuroscience*.
- 6. Myles, D., Bennett, D., Carter, A., Yücel, M., Albertella, L., de Lacy-Vawdon, C., & Livingstone, C. (in press). 'Losses disguised as wins' in electronic gambling machines contribute to win overestimation in a large online sample. Manuscript accepted for publication in Addictive Behaviors Reports.
- Weber, I., Zorowitz, S., Niv, Y., & Bennett, D. (2022). The effects of induced positive and negative affect on Pavlovian-instrumental interactions. *Cognition* and *Emotion*, 36(7), 1343-1360.
- 8. **Bennett**, **D.**, Davidson, G., & Niv, Y. (2022). A model of mood as integrated advantage. *Psychological Review*, 129(3), 513-541.
- 9. **Bennett, D.**, Niv, Y., & Langdon, A. J. (2021). Value-free reinforcement learning: Policy optimization as a minimal model of operant behavior. *Current Opinion in Behavioral Sciences*, 41, 113-121.
- Smillie, L. D., Bennett, D., Tan, N. P., Sutcliffe, K., Fayn, K., Bode, S., & Wacker, J. (2021). Does openness/intellect predict sensitivity to the reward value of information? Cognitive, Affective, and Behavioral Neuroscience, 21(5), 993-1009.
- 11. Zorowitz, S., **Bennett, D**., Choe, G. & Niv, Y. (2021). A recurring reproduction error in the administration of the Generalized Anxiety Disorder Scale. *The Lancet Psychiatry*, 8(3), 180-181.
- Bennett, D., Sutcliffe, K., Tan, N. P., Smillie, L. D., & Bode, S. (2021). Anxious and obsessive-compulsive traits are independently associated with valuation of non-instrumental information. *Journal of Experimental Psychology: General*, 150(4), 739-755.
- 13. Goh, A. X.-A., **Bennett, D.**, Bode, S., & Chong, T. T.-J. (2021). Neuro-computational mechanisms underlying the subjective value of information. *Communications Biology*, 4(1), 1-14.
- 14. **Bennett**, **D.**, & Niv, Y. (2020). Opening Burton's clock: Psychiatric insights from computational cognitive models. Chapter in *The Cognitive Neurosciences*, 6th edition (M. Gazzaniga, ed.).
- 15. **Bennett**, **D.**, Silverstein, S., & Niv, Y. (2019). The two cultures of computational psychiatry. *JAMA Psychiatry*, 76 (6), 563-564.
- 16. **Bennett, D.\***, Sasmita, K.\*, Maloney, R. T., Murawski, C., & Bode, S. (2019). Monetary feedback modulates performance and electrophysiological indices of belief updating in reward learning. *Psychophysiology*, 56(10), e13431.

- 17. Bode, S., Feuerriegel, D., **Bennett, D**., & Alday, P. M. (2019). The Decision Decoding ToolBOX (DDTBOX): A multivariate pattern analysis toolbox for event-related potentials. *Neuroinformatics*, 17(1), 27-42.
- Sewell, D., Warren, H. A., Rosenblatt, D., Bennett, D., Lyons, M., & Bode, S. (2018). Feedback discounting in probabilistic categorization: converging evidence from EEG and cognitive modelling. Computational Brain and Behavior, 1(2), 165-183.
- Bode, S., Bennett, D., Sewell, D., K., Paton, B., Egan, G. F., Smith, P. L., & Murawski, C. (2018). Dissociating neural variability related to stimulus quality and response times in perceptual decision-making. *Neuropsychologia*, 111, 190-200.
- 20. Brydevall, M.\*, **Bennett, D.**\*, Murawski, C., & Bode, S. (2018). The neural encoding of information prediction errors during non-instrumental information seeking. *Scientific Reports*, 8, 6134.
- 21. **Bennett**, **D.**, Yücel, M., & Murawski, C. (2018). Errors of statistical inference in the Information Sampling Task. *Biological Psychiatry*, 83(12), e61-e62.
- Bennett, D., Oldham, S., Dawson, A., Parkes, L., Murawski, C., & Yücel, M. (2017). Systematic overestimation of reflection impulsivity in the Information Sampling Task. *Biological Psychiatry*, 82(4), e29-e30.
- Carter, O., Bennett, D., Nash, T., Arnold, S., Brown, L., Cai, R.Y., Allan, Z., Dluzniak, A., McAnally, K., Burr, D., & Sundram, S. (2017). Sensory integration deficits support a dimensional view of psychosis and are not limited to schizophrenia. *Translational Psychiatry*, 7, e1118.
- Bennett, D., Bode, S., Brydevall, M., Warren, H., & Murawski, C. (2016). Intrinsic valuation of information in decision making under uncertainty. PLoS Computational Biology, 12(7), e1005020.
- 25. Bennett, D., Dluzniak, A., Cropper, S., Partos, T., Sundram, S., & Carter, O. (2016). Selective impairment of global motion integration, but not global form integration, in schizophrenia and bipolar affective disorder. Schizophrenia Research: Cognition, 3, 11-14.
- 26. **Bennett**, **D.** (2015). The neural mechanisms of Bayesian belief updating. *The Journal of Neuroscience*, 35(50), 16300-16302.
- 27. **Bennett**, **D.**, Murawski, C., & Bode, S. (2015). Single-trial event-related potential correlates of belief updating. *eNeuro*, 2(5), 1-14.
- 28. Bode, S., **Bennett, D.**, Stahl, J., & Murawski, C. (2014). Distributed patterns of event-related potentials predict subsequent ratings of abstract stimulus attributes. *PLoS One*, 9(10), e109070.

Extended abstracts in peer-reviewed conference proceedings

- 29. **Bennett, D.** (2022). No evidence for short-timescale temporal declines in expectations within a controlled cognitive task. *Proceedings of the 44th Annual Meeting of the Cognitive Science Society*.
- 30. **Bennett, D.**, Davidson, G., & Niv, Y. (2019). Momentum and mood in policy-gradient reinforcement learning. The 4th Multidisciplinary Conference on Reinforcement Learning and Decision Making.

31. **Bennett, D.**, Feuerriegel, D., Alday, P. M., & Bode, S. (2017). The Decision Decoding ToolBOX (DDTBOX): A multivariate pattern analysis toolbox for event-related potentials. *Conference on Cognitive Computational Neuroscience* 2017.

\* Denotes equal contribution

Grants and funding

Activation Fund (AUD \$20,000 + GBP £10,000)

2022

Monash-Warwick Alliance Role: Chief investigator

Project title: Building an online data-collection platform for in-play sports betting

Turner Institute Strategic Project Grants Scheme (AUD \$20,000)

2022

The Turner Institute for Brain and Mental Health, Monash University

Role: Chief investigator

Project title: Using computational cognitive science to tackle cash-out gambling

Sir Keith Murdoch Graduate Fellowship (USD \$40,000)

2019

American-Australian Association

CJ Martin Early Career Fellowship (AUD \$417,192)

2019-2022

National Health and Medical Research Council

Role: Chief investigator

Project title: Towards a neurocomputational model of mood instability in psychiatric

illness.

Awards

Best ECR Presentation

2020

Australasian Society for Bipolar Disorder and Depression - ECR Webinar Series

Travel Fellowship Award (USD \$2,000)

2020

Society of Biological Psychiatry

Career Development Award (AUD \$1,500)

2016

School of Psychological Sciences, The University of Melbourne

Postgraduate student presentation award

2015

School of Psychological Sciences, The University of Melbourne

Melbourne Abroad Travelling Scholarship (AUD \$1,500)

2014

The University of Melbourne

Australian Postgraduate Award (AUD \$92,008)

2013-2016

Postgraduate research scholarship, Australian Federal Department of Education

Dwight Prize for Honours in Psychology

2011

For coursework in Psychology at The University of Melbourne

Dean's Honours List in Science

2011

For coursework in the Bachelor of Science at The University of Melbourne

Convocation, The UWA Graduates Association Prize Award for undergraduate coursework

2008

Commonwealth Accommodation Scholarship

2007-2010

Undergraduate scholarship, Australian Federal Department of Education

Teaching

NB: Where available, student evaluations reflect the most recent year

## Monash University

2022-present

- 2022-present: Lecturer and Chief Examiner, PSY3051 (Perception and Cognitive Psychology). Third-year undergraduate unit,  $\sim$ 400 students, delivered  $\sim$ 10 2-hour lectures.

 ${\bf Student\ evaluation:\ 90/100\ (`Very\ High',\ highest\ possible\ satisfaction\ band)}$ 

- 2022-present: Lecturer and Chief Examiner, PSY3032 (Psychological Disorders).
   Third-year under-graduate unit, ~400 students, delivered 12 1-hour lectures
   Student evaluation: 90/100 ('Very High', highest possible satisfaction band)
- 2022-present: Lecturer, PSY1011 (Psychology 1A). First-year undergraduate unit, ~1200 students, delivered 4 1-hour lectures on learning and memory.
   Student evaluation: 91/100 ('Very High', highest possible satisfaction band).
- 2022: Lecturer, PSY1022 (Psychology 1B). First-year undergraduate unit, ~1200 students, delivered 4 1hr lectures on sensation and perception.
   Student evaluation: 90/100 ('Very High', highest possible satisfaction band).

## Princeton University

2018

 Fall 2018: Postdoctoral Tutorial Leader, Junior Neuroscience Tutorial. Responsibilities: design, deliver, and assess a 6-week intensive undergraduate neuroscience tutorial series.

## University of Melbourne

2011-2016

- 2016: Lecturer, PSYC40004 (Current Topics in Cognitive Neuroscience). Honourslevel unit, ~ 80 students, deliver 1 2-hr lecture on decision making.
- 2015: Tutor, PSYC30018 (Neuroscience and the Mind). Third-year undergraduate unit, tutorial delivery and marking for two classes.
- 2011-2012: Non-residential tutor in Psychology. Responsibilities: design and deliver first-year psychology coursework tutorials at residential colleges (Janet Clarke Hall, Newman College, St. Mary's College, University College).

### Supervision

PhD

- 2023-present: PhD co-supervisor for Jocelyn Halim (Monash University)
- 2023-present: PhD co-supervisor for Chanel Agosto (Monash University)
- 2022-present: PhD co-supervisor for Chuyin Zhang (Monash University)

- 2022-present: PhD co-supervisor for Jeryl Lim (Monash University)
- 2017-2020: PhD co-supervisor for Ariel Goh (Monash University)

#### *Honours*

- 2023: Antonia Cholewick, Ong George Ngieng, Brody Quinn, and Hirushi Weerakoon
- 2022: Cassandra Dods, Robert Shirley, and Jianming Zhu
- 2021: Laura Forbes and Ashleigh Fulton
- 2014-2017: Assistant supervision for 6 Honours students at The University of Melbourne (primary supervision by Olivia Carter or Stefan Bode)

#### Undergraduates and interns

- 2022: Samuel Arsovski, Antonia Cholewick, and Chantel Wormington
- 2019-2020: Senior thesis co-supervisor for Claire Lee (Princeton University)
- 2019-2020: Junior project co-supervisor for Isla Weber (Princeton University)

# Professional service

## Reviewing (journal articles)

Behavioural Processes; Biological Psychiatry; Cerebral Cortex; Cognition & Emotion;
 Cognitive, Affective, and Behavioral Neuroscience; Cognitive Psychology; Computational
 Brain & Behavior; Computational Psychiatry; Current Opinion in Behavioral
 Sciences; Decision; eLife; Frontiers in Human Neuroscience; Journal of Affective
 Disorders; Journal of Behavioral Decision Making; Journal of Cognitive Neuroscience;
 Journal of Experimental Psychology: General; Journal of Individual Differences;
 Journal of Neuroscience; NeuroImage; Nature Human Behaviour; PLOS Computational
 Biology; PLOS One; Psychiatry & Clinical Neurosciences; Psychonomic Bulletin
 & Review; Psychological Medicine; Psychological Review; Psychophysiology; Schizophrenia
 Research; Translational Psychiatry.

### Reviewing (funding)

- American-Australian Association (USA to Australia program and Australia to USA program)
- German Research Foundation (Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft)
- Swiss National Science Foundation (Sinergia scheme and Projects scheme)

#### External examining

- 2022: External PhD examiner for Henrik Siljebråt, Goldsmiths' College
- 2021: External PhD examiner for Tim Loossens, KU Leuven

### Other service

- 2022-present: Head of Cognition and Emotion Laboratory at Monash University.
- 2022-present: Sole administrator of the Melbourne Cognitive Science List (jobs and events mailing list distributed to  $\sim$ 350 people).
- 2018-2019: Member of seminar series organising committee, Princeton Neuroscience Institute.
- 2016: Graduate student representative for external relations committe, Melbourne School of Psychological Sciences

<ul> <li>2016: Workshop co-organiser, "Multivariate Analysis of Event-Relate University of South Australia, Adelaide</li> </ul>	d Potentials",
Last update	ed June 2023